<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <lb/>
            <ab><num type="volume" value="2">Vol. II,</num>
               <num type="issue" value="3">No. 4</num>
               <date when="1957-05-03">May 3, 1957</date></ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>Man's ever-present curiosity and interest in world affairs shows itself even in the
               isolated world of Antarctica. At both the <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">MCMURDO
                  SOUND</placeName> and <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName>
               bases weekly newspapers are being printed.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The enthusiastically received "McMurdo News" contains national and international news
               and station items. There are also a chaplain's corner, "Aerological dartboard"
               (weather summary), doctor's column, and personality profiles.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The Little America Publication is called "The Penguin Post." The paper is
               mimeographed Saturday night and delivered to the barracks and officers' quarters,
               ready for Sunday morning readers. Stateside papers were never devoured more avidly
               than these. With no TV or newsreels, only static-punctuated short-wave, and no
               current U.S. magazines, everyone is parched for news.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"The Penguin Post" features include "News of the World Beyond US," "News of the World
               Around Us," (Antarctica), sports, science notes, Man of the Week, weather roundup,
               chaplain's column, Letters to the Editor, jokes and cartoons, entertainment, and
               society section (personals). The paper averages eight pages.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Name for the Little America paper was selected by the local Senate. Wide-spread
               interest was indicated by the fact that 85 names were submitted for the paper
               including "Deep Freeze Breeze," "Ice-O-Lated Post," "Crevasse Crier," and "Sastrugi
               Sayings."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"Penguin Post" is co-edited by the Navy and IGY men. Editors are <persName
                  ref="#CalvinLLarson">Calvin L. Larsen</persName>, chief photographer's mate, of
                  <placeName ref="#CulbertsonMT">Culbertson, Mont.</placeName>, and <persName
                  ref="#RobertCTaylor">Ronald C. Taylor</persName>, IGY Meteorologist, of <placeName
                  ref="#SanGabrielCA">San Gabriel, Calif</placeName>. Reporters are <persName
                  ref="#WilliamFKraut">William F. Kraut</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName
                  ref="#BridgeportCT">Bridgeport, Conn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#BoydDRussell"
                  >Boyd D. Russell</persName>, radioman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#FortWorthTX"><choice>
                     <sic>Forth</sic>
                     <corr>Fort</corr>
                  </choice> Worth, Tex.</placeName>; <persName ref="#PaulCDalrymple">Paul C.
                  Dalrymple</persName>, IGY Glaciologist, of <placeName ref="#CochituateMA"
                  >Cochituate, Mass.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#BruceJLieske">Bruce J.
                  Lieske</persName>, IGY Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SilverSpringsMD">Silver
                  Springs, Md</placeName>. <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Chaplain John E.
                  Zoller</persName> of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich.</placeName>, is
               advisor.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> is also considering adding
               several "foreign correspondents" to the Post staff in the form of "ham" radio
               operators in various areas of the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>AROUND THE BASES --(<date when="1957-04-30">April 30</date>)--<placeName
                  ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>: A 16 by 20 foot gymnasium has
               been completed behind the recreation hall. Heaters have been installed in the
               theatre. Furniture, shelves and cabinets are 20% completed in the library. An R4D of
               VX-6 has made one local flight. A second flight was aborted when the plane's wing tip
               dragged at takeoff, causing minor damage....<placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo"
                  >NAFMcMurdo</placeName>: Ice runway is in good condition. Ice in channel broken by
               Glacier has reached a thickness of 40 inches......<placeName ref="ByrdStation">Byrd
                  Station</placeName>: Tunnel which was partially collapsed by snow has been
               repaired and strengthened...<placeName ref="WilkesStation">Wilkes
               Station</placeName>: Minor building damage was sustained when 83-knot winds arched
               roofs. </p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p><placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName>--(<date when="1957-04-29"
                  >April 29</date>)--The <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>
               "ham" radio station, KC4USA, made an unusual contact recently. On <date
                  when="1957-04-14">April 14</date>
               <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Carl O. Wyman</persName>, IGY Ionospheric Physicist, of
                  <placeName ref="#PhiladelphiaPA">Philadelphia</placeName>, received a ham radio
               phone call from friends <persName ref="#FrankLeeming">Frank</persName> and <persName
                  ref="#RuthLeeming">Ruth Leeming</persName> of <placeName ref="#RedBankNJ">Red
                  Bank, N.J.</placeName></p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>(<num type="page" value="1">1</num>)</ab>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="1"/>
            <p>The unusual feature of the call was that it originated from the <choice>
                  <sic>Leeming's</sic>
                  <corr>Leemings'</corr>
               </choice> 26 foot cabin cruiser at sea off the New Jersey coast. Leeming called a
               telephone operator via marine radio-telephone; the operator called <persName
                  ref="#JuliusMJMadey">Julius M. J. Madey</persName>, operator of amateur station
               K2KGJ in <placeName ref="#ClarkNJ">Clark, N.J.</placeName>; <persName
                  ref="#JuliusMJMadey">Madey</persName> called <persName ref="#BobbieFGrice">Bobbie
                  F. Grice</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#HubbardTX">Hubbard,
                  Texas</placeName>, who was the radio operator on duty at <placeName
                  ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>; and the radio-telephone contact
               between Leeming and <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> was made
               complete.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The "path" was excellent. <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> was surprised
               even for the experienced amateur operator that he is. He bought his first crystal
               short wave receiver when a boy, and sold newspapers to pay for it.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In 1926, when in the Marine Corps, he built a ham station in Nicaragua and carried
               some of the first emergency humanitarian traffic for service personnel. He was
               communications officer in the Marines, Pacific Theater, during the second World War,
               and in 1948 he was recalled to Washington for active duty with the Electronic Warfare
               Program. Since release from active duty as a Lieutenant Colonel in 1955, he has
               continued ham radio activities. He holds an amateur license number K2VAV.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>At <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>
               <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> will soon start classes for beginners
               desiring to learn code and try for a ham operator's license.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="ByrdStation">
            <p><placeName ref="#ByrdStation">BYRD STATION</placeName> --(<date when="1957-04-29"
                  >April 29</date>)-- At this isolated, inland base, 647 miles west of Little
               America, the last sunrise of the season was witnessed on Easter Sunday morning.
               Special messages were sent and received through the courtesy of "ham" radio
               operators.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>At sunset on Easter Day a tape recording sounded taps and the American flag over Byrd
               station was hauled down for the Antarctic night. There is now a sense of urgency
               about completing the remaining outside work during the few remaining weeks of
               twilight.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p><placeName ref="WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName>--(<date when="1957-04-30"
                  >April 30</date>)-- Much activity is centered around the local ladder cribbage
               tournament. Holding the title within a week were <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala"
                  >Rudolf A. Honkala</persName>, IGY Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SalisburyNH"
                  >Salisbury, N. H.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DavidDaniel">David
                  Daniel</persName>, commissaryman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#FairfieldTX"><choice>
                     <sic>Fairfiled</sic>
                     <corr>Fairfield</corr>
                  </choice>, Texas</placeName>; and <persName ref="#CarolREklund">Carl R.
                  Eklund</persName>, station scientific leader, of <placeName ref="AtlantaGA"
                  >Atlanta, Ga.</placeName></p>
            <lb/>
            <p><persName ref="#RobertLLong">Robert L. Long, Jr.</persName>, Ionospheric Physicist,
               of <placeName ref="RochesterNY">Rochester, N.Y.</placeName>, after trying out a ski
               ride behind three dogs, reported considerable disagreement between where he wanted to
               go and where the dogs went. <persName ref="#BillieRLilienthal">Billie R.
                  Lilienthal</persName>, aerographer's, mate 3/c, of <placeName ref="#AshlandNB"
                  >Ashland, Nebr.</placeName>, has spent his long night watches making slipcovers
               for our badly soiled lounge chairs.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><persName ref="#SidneyEGreen">Sidney E. Green</persName>, construction driver 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#ColbertWA">Colbert, Wash.</placeName>; <persName
                  ref="EdwardABousquet">Edward A. Bousquet</persName>, utilitiesman 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#Worcester">Worcester, Mass.</placeName>; <persName
                  ref="#CarlTBailey">Carl T. Bailey</persName>, Aerographer's mate 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="LeeMA">Lee, Mass.</placeName>; and <persName
                  ref="SheldonWGrinnell">Lt. Sheldon W. Grinnell</persName>, station doctor of
                  <placeName ref="CarbondaleIL">Carbondale, Ill.</placeName>, have spent Sunday
               holidays helping Scientific Leader <persName ref="CarlREklund">Eklund</persName> with
               biological field work.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab><persName ref="#GeorgeEMagee">George E. Magee</persName>, builder 1/c of <placeName
                  ref="MaldenNY">Malden, N.Y.</placeName>, sidelined from his carpentry with a sore
               arm, has been spending much of his time operating the amateur radio station. This has
               helped remove some of the load from <persName ref="#FrederickECharlton">Frederick E.
                  Charlton</persName>, chief electronics technician, of <placeName ref="#MundieIN"
                  >Muncie, Ind.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DoinaldLBradford">Donald L.
                  Bradford</persName>, radioman, 1/c,</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>(<num type="page" value="2">2</num>)</ab>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
            <ab>of <placeName ref="#MesaAZ">Mesa, Ariz.</placeName>; <persName
                  ref="#KennethJHailstorm">Kenneth J. Hailstorm</persName>, radioman 3/c, of Gallup,
               N.M.; and Garth H. Stonehocker, Ionospheric Physicist, of Portsmouth, Va., who had
               been hard pressed trying to make "ham" radio contacts for station personnel.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Paul A. Wyche, aerographer's mate 1/c, of Macon, Ga., is suffering from a sprained
               ankle. He twisted it while carrying water out to the balloon release shelter. Gilbert
               Lewart, IGY Seismologist, of Cloverdale, Calif., has recorded his first earthquake.
               It came from the area south of Australia.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Ralph Glasgal, IGY Auroral Physicist, of New York City, is watching his sleeping
               hours being cut down as the lengthening nights increase the time he must spend making
               observations.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
